# **Abbas Askar**

Nationality: Pakistani

Date of birth: 31 August 1987

**Mailing Address:** 

Box 43,

SE-221 00 Lund

Sweden

**Email:** 

askar@astro.lu.se abbas.askar@gmail.com

Webpage:

https://abbasaskar.com/ **Phone:** +48 887 746 384

As of June 2018, I am a Carl Tryggers postdoctoral researcher at Lund Observatory, Department of Astronomy and Theoretical Physics of Lund University in Sweden. I work on dynamical evolution of dense stellar systems and my research focuses on populations of compact objects and exotic binary systems in globular clusters.

## SCIENTIFIC APPOINTMENTS/POSITIONS

• Lund Observatory, Department of Astronomy and Theoretical Physics, Lund University, Lund, Sweden

**06/2018** to present

Postdoctoral Researcher (Carl Tryggers Fellow)

• Nicolaus Copernicus Astronomical Center, Warsaw, Poland

11/2013 to 05/2018

11/2013 to 05/2018

Graduate Student/Research Assistant

### **EDUCATION**

# • PhD in Astronomy & Astrophysics (with distinction)

Nicolaus Copernicus Astronomical Center (CAMK)

Polish Academy of Sciences, Warsaw, Poland

Supervisor: Dr. Mirek Giersz

Group: Dynamics of Stellar Systems

MOCCA (Monte Carlo Cluster Simulator) Code Team Member

Thesis: "Investigation of Black Hole Populations in Dense Stellar Systems

using MOCCA code for Star Cluster Simulations"

## • Master of Science in Astronomy & Astrophysics

10/2010 to 9/2012

AstroMundus-Erasmus Mundus Joint Masters Program in Astrophysics

University of Innsbruck, Austria (1st semester)

University of Padova, Italy (2<sup>nd</sup> & 4<sup>th</sup> semesters)

University of Belgrade, Serbia (3<sup>rd</sup> semester)

Final Mark: 105/110

## • Bachelor of Science (Honors) & Bachelor of Arts (Honors) in Liberal Arts & Sciences 08/2006 to 07/2009

University College Utrecht, Utrecht University, The Netherlands Double Major in Physical Sciences (Physics & Mathematics)

& Humanities (Philosophy & Religious Studies)

## GCE Advanced & Ordinary Level

University College Lahore, Lahore, Pakistan 5 years of the British high school curriculum

09/2001 to 06/2006

#### REFEREED PUBLICATIONS

• B. Leor, V. Cardoso, S. Nissanke, T. P Sotiriou, A. Askar, C. Belczynski,

G. Bertone, E. Bon, D. Blas, R. Brito & 192 coauthors

Black holes, gravitational waves and fundamental physics: a roadmap

(White Paper for the COST action "Gravitational Waves, Black Holes, and Fundamental Physics" - Submitted).

http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2018arXiv180208654S.

• J. Hong, E. Vesperini, A. Askar, M. Giersz, and M. Szkudlarek:

Binary Black Hole Mergers from Globular Clusters: the Impact of Globular Cluster Properties (Submitted to MNRAS 2018).

• J. Samsing, D.J D'Orazio, A. Askar, and M. Giersz:

Black Hole Mergers from Globular Clusters Observable by LISA and LIGO:

Results from post-Newtonian Binary-Single ScatteringsInteractions In Globular Clusters (Submitted to Phys. Rev. D 2018)

http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2018arXiv180208654S.

• J. Morawski, M. Giersz, A. Askar, and K. Belczynski

MOCCA-SURVEY Database I: Assessing GW kick retention fractions for BH-BH mergers in globular clusters . (Submitted to MNRAS 2018).

http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2018arXiv180201192M

• K. Belczynski, J. Klencki, G. Meynet, C. L Fryer, D. A Brown, M. Chruslinska, W. Gladysz,

R. O'Shaughnessy, T. Bulik, E. Berti, D. Holz, D. Gerosa, M. Giersz, S. Ekstrom, C. Georgy,

A. Askar, J.P Lasota, D. Wysocki:

*GW170104* and the origin of heavy, low-spin binary black holes via classical isolated binary evolution normalsize (Submitted to Journal).

http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2017arXiv170607053B.

• M. Arca-Sedda, A. Askar, and M. Giersz,

MOCCA-SURVEY Database I. Unravelling black hole subsystems in globular clusters. (Submitted to MNRAS 2018).

http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2018arXiv180100795A

• A. Askar, M. Arca-Sedda, and M. Giersz,

MOCCA-SURVEY Database I: Galactic Globular Clusters Harbouring a Black Hole Subsystem. (Vol. 478, Issue 2, p.1844-1854 MNRAS 2018).

http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2018MNRAS.478.1844A

• K. Belczynski, A. Askar, M. Arca-Sedda, M. Chruslinska, M. Donnari, M. Giersz,

M. Benacquista, R. Spurzem, D. Jin, G. Wiktorowicz and D. Belloni:

The The origin of the first neutron star – neutron star merger.

(Accepted for Publication in A&A 2018).

http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2017arXiv171200632B

• J. Samsing, A. Askar, M. Giersz:

MOCCA-SURVEY Database I: Eccentric Black Hole Mergers During Binary-Single Interactions In Globular Clusters (ApJ 2018 Vol. 855, 2, article id. 124, 5 pp.)

http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2018ApJ...855..124S.

• A. Askar, M. Giersz, W. Pych, E. Dalessandro:

COCOA code for creating mock observations of star cluster models (MNRAS 2017 Vol 475, Issue 3, p.4170-4185).

http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2018MNRAS.475.4170A

• J. Hong, R. de Grijs, A. Askar, P. Berczik, C. Li, L. Wang, L. Deng,

M. B. N. Kouwenhoven, M. Giersz, M., R. Spurzem:

The dynamical origin of multiple populations in intermediate-age clusters in the Magellani clouds (MNRAS 2017 Vol 472, 1, p.67-77).

http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2017MNRAS.472...67H

• D.Belloni, **A. Askar**, M. Giersz, P. Kroupa, M.Giersz & H.J, Rocha-Pinto: *On the initial binary population for star cluster simulations* (MNRAS 2017 Vol 471, 3, p.2812-2828).

http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2017MNRAS.471.2812B

• D.Belloni, M. Zorotvic, M.Schreiber, N.W.C Leigh, M.Giersz & A. Askar: MOCCA-SURVEY database I. Accreting white dwarf binary systems in globular clusters – III. Cataclysmic variables – Implications of model assumptions (MNRAS 2017 Vol. 468, 2, p.2429-2446).

http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2017MNRAS.468.2429B

- R.d. Vita, M. Trenti, P. Bianchini, A. Askar, M. Giersz, G. van de Ven: Prospects for detection of intermediate-mass black holes in globular clusters using integrated-light spectroscopy (MNRAS 2017 Vol. 467, 4, p.4057-4066). http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2017MNRAS.467.4057D
- A. Askar, M. Szkudlarek, D.Gondek-Rosińska, M. Giersz, T. Bulik: MOCCA-SURVEY Database I. Coalescing binary black holes originating from globular clusters (MNRASL 2017 Vol. 464, p.L36-L40). http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2017MNRAS.464L..36A
- A. Askar, P. Bianchini, R.d. Vita, M. Giersz, A. Hypki, S. Kamann: *MOCCA-SURVEY Database I: Is NGC 6535 a dark star cluster harbouring an IMBH?* (MNRAS 2017 Vol 464,3, p.3090-3100).

http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2017MNRAS.464.3090A

• D. Belloni, M. Giersz, H.J, Rocha-Pinto, N.W.C Leigh, **A. Askar**: *MOCCA-SURVEY database I. Accreting white dwarf binary systems in globular clusters*- II. Cataclysmic variables - progenitors and population at birth (MNRAS Vol 464, 4, p.4077-4095).

http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2017MNRAS.464.4077B

- D. Belloni, M. Giersz, A. Askar, N.W.C Leigh, A.Hypki: MOCCA-SURVEY database I. Accreting white dwarf binary systems in globular clusters I. Cataclysmic variables present-day population (MNRAS Vol 462, 3, p.2950-2969). http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2016MNRAS.462.2950B
- L. Wang, R. Spurzem, S. Aarseth, M. Giersz, **A. Askar**, P. Berczik, T. Naab, R. Schadow, M. B. N. Kouwenhoven: *The DRAGON simulations: globular cluster evolution with a million stars* (MNRAS Volume 458, 2, p.1450-1465). http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2016MNRAS.458.1450W
- M. Giersz, N. Leigh, A. Hypki, N. Lützgendorf, A. Askar: MOCCA code for star cluster simulations IV. A new scenario for intermediate mass black hole formation in globular clusters (MNRAS Volume 454, 3, p.3150-3165). http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2015MNRAS.454.3150G

## **CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS**

- M. Giersz, N. Leigh, A. Hypki, A. Askar, N. Lützgendorf: Formation mechanisms of IMBH in globular clusters (MmSAI v.87, p.555 2016). http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2016MmSAI..87..555G
- D. Belloni, M. Giersz, A. Askar, Hypki: Cataclysmic variables in globular clusters. First results on the analysis of the MOCCA simulations database (MmSAI v.87, p.551 2016). http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2016MmSAI..87..551B
- A. Askar, M. Giersz, W. Pych, A. Olech, A. Hypki: MOCCA code for star cluster simulation: comparison with optical observations using COCOA (IAU Symposium, Volume 312, pp. 262-263 2016). http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2016IAUS..312..262A
- M. Giersz, N. Leigh, M. Marks, A. Hypki, A. Askar: Monte Carlo modeling of globular star clusters: many primordial binaries and IMBH formation (IAU Symposium, Volume 312, pp. 213-222 2016). http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2016IAUS..312..213G

#### OTHER WORK EXPERIENCE

• SRON Netherlands Institute for Space, Utrecht, The Netherlands Undergraduate Researcher

05/2009 to 07/2009

Worked full time for 3 months on a research project at the High Energy Astrophysics Division of SRON.

• Lahore Law Publications, Lahore, Pakistan

09/2005-02/2006

#### System Analyst & Programmer.

Designed, implemented and tested an order processing system. Internship A-Level Coursework

#### CONFERENCES & TALKS

- Talk on "Black Hole Subsystems in Galactic Globular Clusters" at MODEST 18 (Santorini, Greece 2018)
- Talk on "Investigating Black Hole Populations in Globular Clusters with MOCCA Code for Star Cluster Simulations" at Galileo Galileo Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Padova/INAF-Astronomical Observatory of Padova, Italy 2018).
- Talk on "Investigating Black Hole Populations in Globular Clusters with MOCCA Code for Star Cluster Simulations" at Eötvös Loránd University (Budapest, Hungary 2018).
- Talk on "MOCCA-Survey Database I: Binary Black Holes and Intermediate Mass Black Holes in Globular Clusters" at Numerical Scattering Workshop, Center for Computational Astrophysics, Flatiron Institute, (New York City, USA 2017).
- Talk on "Gravitational Waves and High Energy Sources Originating From Globular Clusters" at MODEST 17 (Prague, Czech Republic 2017).
- Talk on "MOCCA-Survey Database I: Binary Black Holes and Intermediate Mass Black Holes in Globular Clusters" at Lund Observatory Seminar (Lund, Sweden 2017).
- Talk on "MOCCA-Survey Database I: Binary Black Holes and Intermediate Mass Black Holes in Globular Clusters" at Nicolaus Copernicus Center Wednesday Colloqium (Warsaw, Poland 2017).
- Talk on "Binary Black Holes and Intermediate Mass Black Holes in Globular Clusters" at Koło Naukowe Astronomów (Student's Astronomy Circle), University of Warsaw Observatory (Warsaw, Poland 2017).
- Talk on "Coalescing Binary Black Holes Originating from Globular Clusters" at Heraeus-Seminar 61: Stellar Aggregates (Bad Honnef, Germany 2016).
- Talk on "MOCCA-Survey Database I: Binary Black Holes and Intermediate Mass Black Holes in Globular Clusters" at KIAA/Peking University Lunch Talk (Beijing, China 2016).
- Talk on "Merging Binary Black Holes Originating from Globular Clusters" at Astro-GR 2016 Meeting (Benasque, Spain 2016).
- Presented poster on "Simulating Observations of MOCCA Star Cluster Simulations with COCOA" at EES 2015 School on Stellar Clusters (Banyuls sur Mer,France 2015).
- Talk on "Simulating Observations of MOCCA Star Cluster Simulations with COCOA" at MODEST 15 (Concepcion, Chile 2015).
- Poster presentation, "MOCCA Code for Star Cluster Simulations: Comparison with Optical Observations using COCOA" at International Conference of Young Astronomers (Toruń, Poland 2014).
- Poster entitled, "MOCCA Code for Star Cluster Simulations: Comparison with Optical Observations using COCOA" (presented by M. Giersz) at IAUS 312: Star Clusters & Black Holes in Galaxies across Cosmic Time (Beijing, China 2014).
- Presented a talk on "X-ray Bursts" at the 5th Serbian Astronomical Student Workshop hosted by University of Belgrade and University of Novi-Sad (Belgrade, Serbia 2011).

#### MASTERS & UNDERGRADUATE PROJECTS

• Optical Counterparts of Ultraluminous X-ray Sources

03/2012 to 9/2012

Astromundus Course Master Thesis

Supervisor: Dr. Luca Zampieri

INAF-Astronomical Observatory of Padova & Department of Physics & Astronomy

University of Padova, Italy

Grade: 30+/30

## • Peculiar Features in the Onsets of Thermonuclear Flashes on

Neutron Stars 05/2009 to 07/2009

SCI 301: Natural Science Bachelor Thesis Supervisor: Dr. Jean in't Zand (SRON)

High Energy Astrophysics Division, SRON Netherlands Institute for Space Research

Utrecht, The Netherlands

Grade: A

# $\bullet \;\; The \; Problem \; of \; Redemptive \; Truth: From \; Nietzsche \; to \; a$

Post-Metaphysical Culture

05/2008 to 08/2008

HUM 301: Humanities Bachelor Thesis Supervisor: Dr. Floris van der Burg

University College Utrecht, Utrecht University, The Netherlands

Grade: A

## GRANTS, SCHOLARSHIPS & AWARDS

- Carl Tryggers Fellowship for post-doctoral research awarded by the Carl Tryggers Foundation (2018 to 2020)
- Preludium grant for PhD students awarded by the Polish National Science Center (2016 to 2018)
- Nicolaus Copernicus Astronomical Center Grant for Young Researchers (2015 to 2017)
- PhD Scholarship in Stellar Dynamics, National Science Center, Poland (2013 to 2017)
- Erasmus Mundus Scholarship for Master Studies in Astrophysics and Astronomy (2010 to 2012)
- Excellence Scholarship for Undergraduate Studies at University College Utrecht (Utrecht University) (2006-2009)
- Merit Scholarship for A Levels at University College Lahore (2004-2006)
- Award for Excellence in Computing, University College Lahore (2005)

## TEACHING & STUDENT SUPERVISION

- Co-supervised summer student projects at Nicolaus Copernicus Astronomical Center:
  - Jakub Morawski (2017 Bachelor Student, Warsaw Observatory)
  - Piotr Kołodziejski (2016 Bachelor Student, Warsaw Observatory)
  - Jakub Klencki (2016 Master Student, Warsaw Observatory)
  - Piotr Adamczyk (2015 Bachelor Student, Warsaw Observatory)
  - Magdalena Szponar (2015 Bachelor Student, Warsaw Observatory)
- Co-supervised and assisted with Masters thesis project of Riko Schadow (Ludwig Maximilian University of Munich, 2015) and research project by Arthur Kuehlwein (Heidelberg University, 2015)

#### **SKILLS & MISCELLANEOUS**

#### Languages

- Urdu (Native)
- English (Fluent)-TOEFL (Computer Based) Score: 273/300 (February 2006)
- Punjabi (Intermediate Level)
- Dutch (Beginner Level)

#### Computer Skills

- Scientific programming in Python, Fortran, shell scripting, C
- Wolfram Mathematica and MATLAB

# Extracurricular Activities

- Assembled and setup muon detectors at University College Utrecht (Part of HiSparc project)
- Junior Advisor at University College Utrecht (2007-2008)
- Represented University College Lahore in many nationwide quiz competitions (2001 to 2006)
- Member of University College Lahore debating team in All-Pakistan parliamentary style debates at Under 17 & Under 19 Level between 2001 & 2006